go ahead it's like um
everybody talks about how good my
backhand is yeah that's true
for some reason the uh forehand
when i do the forehand when the ball is
coming
i i supposed to move it this way and
kind of like move
forward with the body but what happens
to me is like when i hit the ball
it seems like the ball pushes me back
you're going backwards
yeah yeah you don't feel that on the
backhand
i feel like i'm kind of adjusting myself
on the back end
yeah and it pushes me back you know it's
really interesting because there's
different biomechanics on both
both of those shots and the forehand
will have much more rotation than the
backhand
so sometimes the weight is moving
backwards and what it solely depends on
whether you're going
forward or backward depends on the
incoming ball
go ahead and get up to this ball try it
again
go on the baseline and come up to this
ball
good so there you're moving forward yeah
okay and now
go ahead and hit this one
okay and i'll hit this one here back up
all right so there you caught that one a
little bit late but so basically
what the way you're gonna move on the
forehand depends solely
on the incoming ball so if the ball
doesn't have a lot of penetration you
know what i mean by penetration
like how much the ball is going through
the court how much is it penetrating
through the court so take a look at this
one right here watch
see this one is penetrating quite a bit
you see the second bounce was in the
fence
yeah okay now watch this one look look
at this one
is this one penetrating a lot not really
it bounced like five times before hit
the fence it actually bounced twice
before you hit the baseline take a look
again
there's a backhand slice you see this
one two
three so what happens on a ball like
this this is an extreme example
you cannot wait for that ball so you
have to move forward and get that ball
this is on all shots whether it be
forehand or backhand but specifically on
the forehand
on a ball like this you'll have to move
forward and the most natural way to move
forward
on the forehand is to do it with your
left
side so you're going to step up with
your left side now you might need to
run up to the ball let's just take an
instance where the ball is maybe
halfway between the baseline and the
service line you might be okay just
taking one step
and stepping up to the ball see it's not
like you're stepping
in you're stepping up in relation to the
incoming ball
that makes sense and in that instance
you would actually be going forward
step up today the ball is not coming to
you you got to step up
wanna step up hey look anna you can take
a step like this
take a step and the step can be quite
large you can make a big step towards
the ball okay
make it even bigger come up
better there you go come again
larger again
better okay don't be afraid to step up
to a ball like that
now can you do this on a regular length
ball
you can't because what's going to happen
is if you try to step
up to a ball that's coming with more
penetration now you're going to reduce
the time between the ball
and the contact you're going to have a
very difficult time with the timing
and so in that instance when the ball is
coming with decent pace you actually
don't have to um
go forward at all because the forehand
swing pass take a look
what we learned on the forehand is to
rotate and make contact
in front and then go up across and back
with the racket so
there's really no forward movement of
the racket
after the ball has left the racket it's
an up a cross and back movement so the
body has to accommodate
the swing path and there's no forward
movement
you see so when we don't have to step up
and set up the ball when it's coming
right to us
and the movement is actually going
backwards so you take a look
we're going forward towards the ball
we're making contact and now it goes
up across and back like this so if you
try to go forward
you would actually make the stroke more
difficult you would actually take away
from this natural up across and back
swing pad that you're getting from your
from your torso rotation sequencing that
we learned a while back
right so there's really you don't have
to worry about going forward on the shot
you don't you just worry about finishing
and making sure that you're rotating the
right way
but don't worry about going forward only
you're gonna go forward
when the incoming ball requires you to
do so like i just
like those balls that i just fed to you
does it make sense yeah all right so
stand right here
let me ask you another question go ahead
stand right there
i feel like it's all about positioning
towards the ball
because i often have myself like a
chicken wing like
yeah of course you know yeah like this
instead of
having like a free motion
maybe um it takes time to adjust
myself to the bowl it's such a great
question because
what what that is it's ball recognition
so you're probably not recognizing early
enough how the ball is going to get to
you
you're not set in the right place and
you're forced to improvise either the
ball
it's laterally too close to you meaning
that it's too close to your body
in this way yeah and then you're like
like you said you're chicken wing you'd
have to get out of the way you have to
bend
that's the lateral spacing you're just
not seeing the ball that well
or it's the forward backward spacing
where you think that the ball is coming
to you but it's actually not and then
you end up reaching and going like this
or the ball is going deeper than you
expected it to and all of a sudden you
let the ball get behind you and you're
hitting it back here yeah
so all those circumstances are going to
make the forehand feel feel awful
okay you know so just a matter of you
have to really track the ball and follow
it
very closely as it's flying to you but
also most importantly you have to have
high intensity and move your feet
a lot but when i do the backhand yeah i
understand where i should stand i don't
double question myself how to position
it like for some reason
yeah my brain registered this i know you
know it's the back end is so much more
simple
than the forehand there's more moving
parts on the forehand there's all kind
of different ways you can bend the arm
and there's also a much more open
positions like
open stance on the forehand on the back
end it's mostly closed i would say 90
percent of the backers are going to be
closed stance and it's overall more of a
simple shot you know
yeah so i think that's why you find it
easier yeah however i do think that on
the forehand you're more power than the
backhand
so while you have a little bit more
trouble on your forehead i do think you
get more strength there
while the back end is maybe more
consistent okay so
now i'm gonna feed you the ball and the
ball is going to be coming perfectly to
you where you don't have to like
think about going backwards or forwards
and just think about like
doing the perfect technique okay it's
going to be coming right to you
just hit it just hit it hit the ball but
i'm going to feed it
no you don't need that because the ball
is now going to have more penetration
yeah so it's going to be coming at the
perfect length and you don't really have
to step up to it okay you can just wait
for it you can wait for the ball
good good
good on a much better
again much better just keep rotating all
the way come on
good
much better nice very nice that feel
yeah but you said on one you felt like
you were
couple in moving backwards a couple in
the beginning okay
so let me let me address that okay why
that happens when you feel like you're
falling backwards so what will happen
sometimes
when the ball indeed is coming a little
bit quicker
you if you don't make adjustments in
your footwork and the ball gets a little
bit behind you
then you're going to take it late and
now the weight
of the ball is going to push you
backwards a little bit and that's what's
going to feel really awful when you hit
it
because the contact is going to be too
far behind so what you have to do
is again ball recognition is so huge
because you'll have to
move back prior to setting up for the
shot so you're going to kind of
read that the ball is coming through a
little bit faster you're going to maybe
back up a couple of steps
set and now you have a better chance to
play it in front
that makes sense yeah okay so stay right
here on top of the baseline
i'm going to put this ball behind the
baseline and you're going to have to
back up
and create space you got to make sure
that you leave your body
behind the ball so in other words don't
let the ball get ahead of you
okay good that's all right
those are better come again
okay that one felt like you were going
backwards right okay
do me a favor feed me a couple balls i'm
gonna show you something okay
feed it deep like i was just doing to
you and i'm to show you two different
ways here's one way
watch this you see that
and here's another way watch this
the second one so here's what i did what
happens is if you back up and you're
completely sideways you're backing up
and you're sideways
it's going to be very hard to rotate
okay and you're going to be forced to
hit the ball
sideways like this and then you fall
backwards like this
and then it feels terrible but even
that's an extreme case you could even be
a little bit more
trying to rotate and kind of have your
feet locked and this is going to feel
terrible too
because when the feet are locked like
this your body
your body is blocked and you won't be
able to rotate past this point right
here
so the best thing to do is to actually
allow
the left side to move backwards this is
going to allow you to rotate all the way
watch
so you're backing up you're setting this
leg on the outside this is super
important that this leg is on the
outside
and now from here the left side can go
back and this is going to allow you
to fully rotate and you'll actually be
able to hit it aggressively
when you do it like that you want to try
it yeah that makes sense so
you're going to be a little bit more
open with your feet and you're going to
allow the left side
to move backwards all right here we go
two sideways
do it again don't lock your feet don't
lock them
allow them to move better on it come
again
unlock it and come
lift that left side up just see what
happens lift the left side up and see
what happens
that was actually the best one because
it was a little too far away
there it is better and you're rotating a
lot further come again
better you see what i mean yeah does it
feel freeing yeah it feels
more playful okay here we go
come on
so much better so this is the shot that
you need to do
when the ball is pushing you back yeah
okay so when you're experiencing this
stuff where
you feel like you're you're being pushed
back it can have multiple reasons why
it's happening so that's why it's hard
for me to analyze it could be like i
said it could be ball recognition
but you're not set up well you're
letting the ball get behind you it could
be that and so
if if you set up the ball well and you
are recognizing that it's going to go
deep
and you still feel like you're falling
back then it might be something
technical where
you're either too sideways or your feet
are stuck into the ground and
you can't really rotate so that's the
case
when you feel like you've been pushed
back you set up well allow that left
side
to open you up all the way which will
allow you to have a normal forehand
normal forehand has full torso rotation
goes from here
to here that's a normal forehand so when
we are moving in
different directions on the court it's
gonna be harder to do that yeah
there's also the case if i push you wide
good so you do a better job when you're
moving laterally than backwards
so you don't feel the same problems when
you're moving laterally correct
do you feel better on your forehand when
you're moving this way yeah compared to
this way you move
you feel better about that right yeah i
know you're doing great with that and
let me show you one more thing
concerning
um how to stand on the forehand how to
set up you actually don't need your
racket here let me have your racket
and now just stand right there i'm going
to throw you the ball
you stand right there i'm going to throw
the ball and you just catch you with
your right hand
and then throw it back to me just back
up a couple more steps four hands come
good back to me back hand
okay good and our forehand
okay and backhand come on
good try so you notice something how
you're you're
working with your right side only when
you're setting up
right here no on both sides yeah yeah
yeah
so naturally on the on the backhand
you're going with the right side towards
the ball because that puts the hand
closer to the incoming ball if you did
like this the hand has to go further
across to reach the ball it's more
unnatural
so naturally you go here so that's why
most of the backhands are hit
closed stance like this and most of the
forehands i hit
open stance because it's more natural on
the forehand to go like this than rather
like this
this will make the hand too far back
that makes sense
so now let's check when the ball is a
little bit shorter let's see what
happens naturally
all right so catch this one on the fly
okay catch it on the fly
do it again catch it on the fly ready
okay good all right come back and here
come up
up on the fly yeah do it again
okay and again lunge lunge yeah
catch you on the fly interesting i do it
again
yes back up and come up
good anna nice and do it again
and on the fly come on catch it all
right so
what's happening on the short balls same
as the lateral boss it's more natural
to use a dominant leg okay on the short
ball
however there's going to be a problem on
the forehand from the baseline okay
because this is not something that you
want to do
is make a large step forward because now
when you do this
you will not be able to get to get the
racket back very far you won't be able
to turn much this will lock your body
so this might be okay for example in the
valley or if you're doing a forehand
slice
if you're doing like a forehand
emergency shot squash shot you know
all these shots that are kind of in the
specialty category
it's okay to do the natural way to use
the dominant side
and go like this when it comes to the
forehand like i explained to you in the
beginning
it is easier biomechanically to step
with the non-dominant side because now
naturally we get a little bit more of a
turn and we also get a full take back
and we get a full turn with the torso
does that make sense on the backhand of
course the dominant side is going to be
a lot easier when we're stepping forward
you know that makes sense yeah it knows
what to do right
absolutely you don't really like to
attack the balls and
the body knows how to do it i'm glad you
said that because the body
is going to let you know if you're doing
something that's unnatural
it's gonna feel uncomfortable it's gonna
feel really uncomfortable when you do
something that's not natural
and that's why you don't really have to
think of your feet just think whether
something's feeling comfortable or not
if it feels awful it's probably wrong
sometimes i'm super limber so sometimes
yes
just like doing something over doing
something and that
could be it could be uncomfortable in my
body it could be
when it comes to the like the strokes
because you're using the the arms and
there's so many moving parts it's very
complex
but i'm more specifically talking about
the legs this is where you shouldn't put
too much
thought on the legs and just go by your
feel
you know and move in the most natural
way okay anna so let's do a real test
now and i'm going to rally with you a
little bit
and now the ball is going to be
unpredictable let's see if you um if you
can
number one have a little better ball
recognition and if you can set the ball
up
better and let me know if you feel like
you're falling backwards anytime you
feel your phone backwards
you stop and let me know a little higher
come on
up
okay see that was why
no it wasn't was in so see those last
two balls the one before you had to step
up and the one after you had to back up
you did it on both you stood
in the same place and had to make
improvisations see what happens
so why did this happen because you
didn't recognize the ball early enough
you got to move
you got to move it you got to watch
watch the ball very closely okay
good good
good anna up that one i felt like he
should have stepped up
that ball wasn't coming at you that that
hard with that much penetration i felt
like you could have stepped to that one
a little bit
did you feel the same way or no the last
one no
you didn't see it's going to take a
while to start recognizing this
so this takes a while to develop this
ball recognition okay
yeah let's keep trying come on
good good
okay stay on your toes here we go
ready ana stay on your toes
come on back up see there you completely
sideways
three more good
good
better come better
all right couple more good
up up last one on the last one
come on
good good
much better much better there anna what
do you think do you
does it make sense what i was saying
today yeah do you still feel like you're
being pushed back not as much not as
much but then when you do do you
recognize it yeah
i started recognizing it do you do you
understand how to solve the problem
move your feet and stay behind stay
behind the ball
but not only that but you have to you
have to really study the ball
because sometimes you won't know that
it's coming like behind you
that's the hard part but the the one
thing you can do right away you can be
patient with the ball recognition that's
going to come with time
with more experience what we can do
right away is have more intensity
and always stay on your toes and move
your feet
absolutely alright good job good job
today very nice